KRISTINA ULICNA

PhD Candidate (final year) @ University College London

London, United Kingdom

kristina.smith.ulicna@gmail.com

+44(0)7754385111 (UK)

in linkedin.com/in/KristinaUlicna

twitter.com/KristinaUlicna

github.com/KristinaUlicna

Computational Skills

Strongest programming language: Python

- Machine learning libraries: skimage, sklearn, torch, pytorch lightning, tensorflow 2.0, keras, innereye-deeplearning, btrack, HPACellSegmentator, CSBDeep
- Standard & scientific libraries: jupyter notebooks / conda environments, numpy, scipy, pandas, json, os, matplotlib, pyplot, h5py, tqdm, napari

Work comfortably with **GitHub** (git), **iPython** (jupyter) notebooks, **LaTeX** (overleaf) & **Sigmaplot Statistics** software

Analysis of **DNA sequencing** data:

- SnapGene software: vector construction
- CLC workbench: Sanger sequencing
- Nanopore sequencing platform interface

Laboratory Skills

Molecular biology & vector construction:

- PCR (RT-, colony-, sequential-, nested-)
- Plasmid preparation (mini- & midi-prep)
- Restriction endonuclease gene cloning
- Gateway cloning & Gibson Assembly
- Preparation & purification of mRNA
- r reparation a parmeation of mixtual
- Cell-free protein synthesis (PURExpress)

Cell engineering & tissue culture:

- Stable cell transfection via lipofection or lentiviral & retroviral transduction
- Colony selection with antibiotic titration
- Tet(Dox)-inducible gene expression
- Cell fractionation & organelle isolation
- Induction of cell differentiation (DMSO)
- Cell culture (passaging) with cell lines: MDCK, HeLa, HL60, CH0, HEK-293, MCF-7/ 10A, MDA-MB-231, HMLER, LNCaP, HaCaT

Cell-based assays & imaging platforms:

 IncuCyte ZOOM live-cell analysis system cell proliferation assay with colorimetric cell viability, ratiometric [Ca²⁺] release & fluorimetric protein release assays

Gene expression detection methods:

- SDS-PAGE, Western (dot) blotting
- Immunocytochemistry (IF cell staining)
- Extra- & intracellular flow cytometry
- FACS-sorted clonal cell line expansion

Summary

As a **PhD** researcher at UCL, I apply my programming & laboratory skills in a multi-disciplinary project combining cell biology, computational single-cell tracking & deep learning. I focus on **Python software development** for **large data analysis** to identify biological patterns influencing **cancer cell cycling** control mechanisms. I am a practical, detail-oriented wet-lab scientist with **cell engineering** background, experienced in dry-lab **machine learning research** applied to single-cell biology. I have demonstrated my **leadership skills** in individual & collective settings, which I gained through UK & US work experience in **academic biomedical research** groups & international bio-/medical & **microscopy imaging research** teams in leading **technological companies**, and through my involvement in **volunteering & community projects**.

Education

Oct 2018 -Nov 2022 (expected)

PhD in Biosciences, BBSRC LIDo DTP Programme, UCL | London, UK

- Provisional <u>Thesis</u> Title: "Deep Lineage with Deep Learning: Tracking Single-Cell Heterogeneity within Non-/Cancer Cell Lines", advised by G. Charras & A. R. Lowe
- Fully funded via London Interdisciplinary Doctoral Training Partnership (LIDo DTP)
- Yale Stem Cell Center. Yale School of Medicine exchange visitor: postponed to '22
- Merit-based Scholarships: Talents of the New Europe '19, Students to the World '19

Sep 2014 -Jul 2018

BSc Biomedical Science (Hons), King's College London | London, UK

- First Class Hons (76%) Biomedical Science with Extramural Year in Pharmacology
- Awards & Scholarships: Desmond Tutu Scholarship '14, Best Lay Article Award '15

Research Experience

Mar 2019 -Present

PhD Researcher, the "DeepTree" project @ UCL | London, UK

- Co-developed a robust, supervision-free, deep learning-based tracking pipeline for deep lineage analysis of large time-lapse microscopy data in non-/cancer cell lines
- Published two computational framework manuscripts (U-Net, CNN, btrack multiobject tracking algorithm) with applicability to single cell cycle duration predictions
- Analysed multigenerational lineage trees (>20,000 single cells) to identify heritable proliferation characteristics which predispose cells to commit to fast divider fates
- Supervised Masters Thesis project to develop an Al-based cell segmentation tool

Apr 2021 -Sep 2021

Research Intern @ Microsoft Research Cambridge | Cambridge, UK

- Developed an Al-based end-to-end pipeline to classify subcellular protein localisation in single cells from Human Protein Atlas' dataset of weakly labelled confocal microscopy images using Azure computing & InnerEye Deep Learning OS toolkit
- Trained a competitively-performing model upon evaluation with Kaggle competition authors (Prof. Emma Lundberg's Lab; manuscript in preparation)
- Summarised project to Health Intelligence Lab leadership at End-of-Internship talk

Sep 2016 -Aug 2017

Industrial Trainee @ Crescendo Biologics Ltd. | Cambridge, UK

- Engineered novel, universal tool cell line for early drug discovery, i.e. phage display selection & functional screening of antibody fragment oncology therapeutics
- Presented project outcomes to senior scientists & company management board

Jun 2016 -Sep 2016

Cancer Research UK Intern @ Cambridge University | Cambridge, UK

 S. Bohndiek Lab: Characterised anti-angiogenic drug effects via breast cancer cell-based growth, viability assays to evaluate oxygen role in cancer progression

Jun 2015 -Aug 2015

Visiting Scholar, Whitehead Institute @ MIT | Cambridge, USA

 R. Weinberg's Lab: Investigated determinants of cancer cell invasion, metastasis & tumour stroma immunomodulation upon epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition

Teaching Experience

May 2021

"Smart Microscopy" Workshop @ ZEISS | Gothenburg, Sweden

 Trained 30+ intermediate-level attendees at "<u>Train Your Own Model</u>" hands-on workshop session to use (bio)image analysis tools (*napari*, *jupyter notebooks*) to annotate cell imaging data to train deep learning model to classify cell cycle state

Jan 2021 -Dec 2021

Google Certified Trainer for AI Tech & Tools | Bratislava, Slovakia

• Empowering non-tech professionals by leveraging their expertise & leadership in Al tech field via Al-basics talks & workshops with Google Slovakia outreach team

Mar 2020 -Present

Graduate Teaching Assistant @ UCL BIOC0016 module | London, UK

 Co-designed an iPython-based <u>practical session</u> for 70+ undergraduate students for introductory concepts in bioimage analysis, bioinformatics & machine learning to hand-label image mini-dataset & train simplified classifier of cell mitotic state

Jun 2020

"Introduction to Deep Learning" @ UCL Cancer Domain | London, UK

- Delivered beginner-friendly <u>masterclass series</u> for 100+ interdisciplinary scientists with real-life examples of deep learning-based bioimage analysis from PhD project
- Demonstrated deep learning benefits, contrasted deep learning to computer vision methods, emphasised fundamentals of 'learning' component & current challenges

Language Skills

Slovak native proficiency

Czech bilingual proficiency

English full professional proficiency

IELTS & iBT TOEFL language test certificates

rman limited working proficiency

High-school certificate; German evening classes

Awards & Scholarships

- 2021 **30 under 30** @ Forbes Slovakia
- 2019 European Union Council Delegate
- 2017 **United Nations** Assembly Delegate
- 2017 GSK Healthcare STEM Awardee

Hobbies & Interests

- Ballroom dancing; standard & Latin style (UK national partner competitions level)
- Bachata & salsa social dancing (int/adv)
- Long-distance running (half-marathons)
- Playing tennis (competitively at school)

General -

- Member of the University of London DanceSport Society (active competitor)
- Member of London Stem Cell Network
- Member of British Pharmacol Society
- EU / Slovak driving licence | B type
- First aid training course certificate

Academic Referees -

Prof Guillaume Charras

- PhD project advisor; Professor in Cell & Tissue Biophysics @ London Centre for Nanotechnology & Dept. of Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- Web: https://charraslab.com/
- Email: g.charras@ucl.ac.uk

Dr Alan R. Lowe

- PhD project advisor; Al for Science Fellow @ The Alan Turing Institute & Associate Professor of Biophysics at Inst. of Struct. & Molec. Biology @ UCL
- Web: http://lowe.cs.ucl.ac.uk/
- Email: a.lowe@ucl.ac.uk

Prof Geraint Thomas

- LIDo PhD Programme Deputy Director;
 Professor of Biochemistry at Dept. of
 Cell & Developmental Biology @ UCL
- Web: https://www.lido-dtp.ac.uk/Email: g.thomas@ucl.ac.uk

Leadership & Teamwork Experience

Student Ambassador, LIDo PhD Programme @ UCL Sep 2019 -I London, UK Present • Outlined programme structure & shared own experience with new student cohorts · Guided individual students through responsibilities with changing rotation projects 2015 -Jury Member, LEAF Award @ LEAF I Bratislava, Slovakia 2017 · Shortlisted self-driven, talented students with community involvement in jury team 2016 -University Mentor. Talent Guide @ LEAF I Bratislava, Slovakia 2018 · Counselled college choices with gifted high-schoolers & edited personal statements

Specialist Trainings & Summer Schools

operance reasoning a canonic concern			
Nov - Dec 2020	Jumping Rivers Ltd. • Two intermediate courses: 'Machine Learning with Pytl	London, UK hon', 'Python & Tensorflow'	
Aug - Sep 2019	University of Hong Kong • Practical course 'Advanced Imaging: Deep Learning in L	Hong Kong, China live Imaging & Cell Biology	
Jun - Jul 2019	University of Genova • 'Machine Learning Crash Course' covering theoretical for	Genova, Italy oundations & core concepts	
Sep - Oct 2016	University of Cambridge • Two beginners courses: 'Solving Biological Problems', 'S	Cambridge, UK Statistical Analysis' using R	
Jun - Jul 2012	Johns Hopkins University • Interactive class 'The History of Disease' by Centre for	Baltimore, USA Talented Youth (CTY JHU)	

		,		
Science Popularisation Activities				
Sep 2015	Universal Expo Milano 2015 Milano Presented ongoing research as national team member to expert & lay aud	n, Italy dience		
May 2014	Intel International Science & Engineering Fair Los Angeles Shortlisted finalist at world's largest pre-college science competition (positions)	-		
Jul 2013	 International Congress of Young Investigators Zaragoza, Invited as 'Absolute Winner at the Festival of Science & Technology' & of 'The Special Award by the Dean of the Faculty of Natural Sciences' 	-		
Nov 2012	Festival of Science & Technology • Recognised as 'Best Scientific Project at Festival of Science & Technology			

Invited Talks

2021	Speaker Machine Learning Methods Advances @ Recursion CytoData Society Meeting Speaker Al Microscopy Symposium @ The Allen Institute for Brain Science & AlVIA Panelist "See the Hidden": Future of Al in Microscopy Workshop @ Leica Microsystems Panelist "Women in Al for Global Health" Session @ Mozilla Festival Tech Conference
2020	Speaker UCL BioImage Analysis Interest Group @ Laboratory of Molecular Cell Biology Speaker Imperial College Brain Sciences Seminar @ UK Dementia Research Institute Speaker Python Software Foundation Pro Network Meetup @ #PyLadies Dublin

Contributed Talks

2021	Poster	Crick Biolmage Analysis Symposium (CBIAS) @ The Francis Crick Institute Women in Data Science (WiDS) Worldwide Conference @ Stanford University Virtual Seminars in Biomedical Science @ Imperial College London
2020	Poster	London Stem Cell Network Annual Symposium @ The Francis Crick Institute Society of Biomolecular Imaging & Informatics High Content Conference UCL Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Postgraduate Symposium
2019	Speaker	UCL Institute of Structural & Molecular Biology Friday Wrap @ Birkbeck Quantitative Systems Biology Workshop @ King's College London UCL Graduate Student Symposium @ Francis Crick Institute

2021 Poster | Women in Machine Learning (WiML) Workshop @ NeurIPS Conference

Publications

Ulicna, K., Vallardi, G., Charras, G. & Lowe, A.R. (2021). Automated deep lineage tree analysis using a Bayesian single cell tracking approach. Frontiers in Computer Science, Computer Vision: Methods & Tools for Bioimage Analysis | Frontiers | BioRxiv | GitHub repository

Ulicna, K., Ho, L.T.L., Soelistyo, C.J., Day, N.J. & Lowe, A.R. (2022). Convolutional neural networks for classifying chromatin morphology in live cell imaging. Methods in Molecular Biology, Springer Nature Protocols (accepted; in press) | GitHub repository